<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pi GATE — Sheffield Pi-Tronics</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://pi.gate.ac.uk/feeds/fred-sonnenwald.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Solar MoPi</title><link>/posts/2014/08/03/solar-mopi/</link><description>

&lt;p&gt;In some of the sunny days we've had this summer, we've managed to try out
hooking up Solar Panels as one of the power inputs to MoPi. The results are
pretty good. A fairly decent panel setup can power even the Model B
completely. In lower light levels or with less powerful panels, they can help
increase battery life. We managed up to 19 hours with a Model B and 8 AAs by
shutting down overnight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/mopi/graphs/solar/mopisolar.2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's pretty good. Those spikes are when the panels overpower the batteries
completely. The next step is to work out how to charge in those conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/mopi.html#solar"&gt;Read more in the main article!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-08-03:posts/2014/08/03/solar-mopi/</guid><category>kickstarter</category><category>batteries</category><category>solar</category><category>mo-pi</category><category>pi-tronics</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category><category>batteries</category></item><item><title>AA battery life with the Model A and Model B</title><link>/posts/2014/07/27/battery-life/</link><description>

&lt;p&gt;We've conducted some tests to help people get a feel for how long AA batteries
should power a Rasberry Pi in a variety of configurations when using MoPi. We
don't have results from &lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/07/15/model-b-plus/"&gt;the B+ yet&lt;/a&gt;, but
that's coming soon...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now though, the best case scenario? &lt;b&gt;50 hours&lt;/b&gt; using the Model A with 16
AAs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/mopi/graphs/mopia2.16fresh.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's best case, of course, with the Pi not doing anything much, but it does
illustrate the potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/mopi.html#detailed-testing"&gt;Read more in the main article!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-07-27:posts/2014/07/27/battery-life/</guid><category>kickstarter</category><category>batteries</category><category>mo-pi</category><category>pi-tronics</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category><category>batteries</category></item><item><title>The AirPi Software</title><link>/posts/2014/04/21/airpisoftware/</link><description>

&lt;!--%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OK, it's been a while. For those that don't remember, the &lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://airpi.es/"&gt;AirPi&lt;/a&gt; is a low-cost weather station add-on project for the Raspberry Pi. I've
previously written about &lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/02/07/airpi1/"&gt;building it from
scratch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/02/14/airpiupdate/"&gt;soldering it up&lt;/a&gt;, and then most
recently &lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/02/25/airpisensors/"&gt;interpreting sensor readings&lt;/a&gt;.
Since then I've been working on making those readings more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's the beauty of open source software and projects really. Tom Hartley (the
AirPi guy) posted their software on &lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/tomhartley/AirPi"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, an open software source code repository. I
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/guruthree/AirPi"&gt;forked it&lt;/a&gt;, or created a copy of the
code, to make my own modifications. After two months of on and off again
changes and testing, I feel it's about as done as it's going to get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal here is to introduce everyone to what I think are the really nifty
things I've added in. I've fixed a few bugs in the original code as I've found
them. I've also then fixed the bugs I introduced myself in the new code, but we
can gloss over them... The big fix I think is the high CPU load the software
had, which only needed the addition of a simple &lt;tt&gt;time.sleep()&lt;/tt&gt; to make it more
reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of the new features is &lt;b&gt;Raingauge Support&lt;/b&gt;. Previously I
&lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/01/25/raingauge/"&gt;looked at them&lt;/a&gt;, and now I've translated the
logging code I wrote there and applied it to the AirPi framework. We've just
gotten even more weather-station-esqe. Just connect the raingauge to GPIO pin
17 and ground. In a similar vein I also added back in support for the &lt;b&gt;TGS-2600
Air Quality Sensor&lt;/b&gt; and the &lt;b&gt;UVI-01 Ultra Violet Sensor&lt;/b&gt;. This was all pretty
trivial still. This was all mostly just extensions of what was already there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/software/raingauge2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/software/raingauge2_thumb.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The raingauge connection...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On to more exciting things! Last time I more or less pointed out that a chunk
of the sensor readings were uncalibrated. Not anymore! There's now a module
that let's the software output calibrated readings. &amp;quot;What's the use?&amp;quot; you
might say? Ah well, for starters I also added a CSV output module. The AirPi
is now compatible with industry standard file formats... also known as a
(comma separated value) spreadsheet. It get's better than that though:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;... (wait for it) ... The Crown Jewels:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/software/webinterface.png"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/software/webinterface_small.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of uploading to Xively, which requires Internet access and relies on a
third-party service, I've &lt;b&gt;built in an HTTP server&lt;/b&gt;. Starting the AirPi
software with this module enabled starts the Pi listening on port 8080
for HTTP requests. Going there loads up a pretty, but fast site that's based
on &lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://getbootstrap.com/"&gt;Twitter Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait! There's more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/software/webinterface2.png"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/software/webinterface2_thumb.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only can you see the current reading, you can also view graphs.
Interactively explore what the weather's been doing over the last 24 hours
with the click of a button. This is of course customizable. You could show the
last hour or the last 2 weeks, but longer periods require more free memory and
will load a bit slower. Check out our &lt;b&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/airpi_demo/"&gt;interactive demo site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. It's not a real Pi there for reasons of my router
being unhappy, but it behaves just like the real thing. Open the drop down to
bring up a graph. Select an area on a graph to zoom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharp eyed observes will have also noticed the RSS feed icon in the upper right
hand corner. This is to allow for easy export of results to other software. I
suspect minimal modifications will allow
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/uduncanu/AirPi/commit/9e13c3ab0e902d563a78e98addc7aac6eda5a35e"&gt;this JSON output&lt;/a&gt; module to be served over HTTP for easy export as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I was after RSS? How many people have heard of
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://conky.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Conky&lt;/a&gt;? It's a system monitor applet that
displays system information on the screen in a corner of the desktop. It's a
bit like the gadgets of Windows Vista/7 or OS X dashboard widgets. Well,
anyway Conky, like gadgets or widgets, supports RSS feeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;=== ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 feed_title} ===
${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_title 0}: ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_desc 0}
${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_title 1}: ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_desc 1}
${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_title 2}: ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_desc 2}
${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_title 3}: ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_desc 3}
${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_title 4}: ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_desc 4}
${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_title 5}:
  ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_desc 5}
${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_title 6}: ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_desc 6}
${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_title 7}: ${rss http://airpi:8080/rss.xml 10 item_desc 7}&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding the above bit of config to the end of my &lt;tt&gt;.conkyrc&lt;/tt&gt; file gives me this
(below) in the upper right corner of my desktop. The weather on my terms. Just
what an AirPi should do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/software/conky.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-04-21:posts/2014/04/21/airpisoftware/</guid><category>airpi</category><category>hardware</category><category>pi-tronics</category><category>environmental</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category></item><item><title>Interpreting AirPi Sensor Readings</title><link>/posts/2014/02/25/airpisensors/</link><description>

&lt;!--%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a few posts now I've been talking about the &lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://airpi.es/"&gt;AirPi&lt;/a&gt;, an
environmental monitoring platform for the RaspberryPi. At the end of
&lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/02/07/airpi1/"&gt;these&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/02/14/airpiupdate/"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;
posts, I made the point that while it's great that I've got output from the
AirPi it doesn't mean much if I don't know what it means. Today I'll be going
through the output (below) and looking at the sensor specs in more details to
get an idea of what the numbers mean. Apologies for a potentially boring very
texty post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;Temp-DHT:       26.1 C
Humidity:       35.7 %
Air Quality:    16920.56
Light Level:    4.91 Lux
UV Level:       0.48 UVI
Temp-BMP:       25.6 C
Pressure:       97912.6 Pa
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;Time: 2014-02-11 20:37:56.611572
Temperature: 32.4 C
Pressure: 977.71 hPa
Relative_Humidity: 25.7000007629 %
Light_Level: 7698.96193772 Ohms
Nitrogen_Dioxide: 7607.57314974 Ohms
Carbon_Monoxide: 301176.470588 Ohms
Volume: 90.3225806452 mV
Uploaded successfully&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The DHT22 (humidity)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the combined temperature moisture probe. It's an
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://www.adafruit.com/products/385"&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt; special, which means I can
start there for learning more. &lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/DHT22.pdf"&gt;The datasheet&lt;/a&gt; is of course
another good source. The two important bits from the Adafruit page are these
two pieces of information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good for 0-100% humidity readings with 2-5% accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good for -40 to 80&amp;deg;C temperature readings &amp;plusmn;0.5&amp;deg;C accuracy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A responses range of 0% to 100% humidity means that it's OK to put a DHT22
pretty much anyplace other than a rainforest. A rainforest, and anyplace else
extraordinarily wet is a no go because checking the datasheet that's 100%
&lt;em&gt;Relative Humidity&lt;/em&gt; (RH). (See &lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humidity"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; for a
bit more about humidity. Effectively once the air is super-saturated for the
temperature we're over 100% RH and so the sensor won't be very happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some good news is that the data sheet says this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calibrated digital signal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fully interchangeable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nominally then every sensor is identical and should give the same reading given
identical conditions. In practice this is very rarely the case. We know this
for sure given the &amp;quot;2-5&lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&amp;quot; accuracy claim. Reading the datasheet again, this
comes across as typically &amp;plusmn;2% accuracy, with a maximum of &amp;plusmn;5%. In most cases
then the reading should be fairly accurate. Because the sensor is digital,
there's also no need to take into account anything in the circuit, so we don't
need to do anything to the values produced by the software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sensor resolution is tenths of a percent (see the 35.7% of above). Based
on &amp;plusmn;2% accuracy, this number could be anywhere from 33.7% to 37.7% RH.
Hopefully sensor error falls along a normal distribution, meaning that if we
collect data on trends over time, something like a moving average will give a
more accurate reading by averaging out the effect of errors. The moral here is
don't be lulled by that extra 0.1% humidity, that on its own won't make a
difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeatability is another factor to consider, independent of accuracy. The
datasheet says &amp;plusmn;1%, which means sequential readings given identical conditions
will still vary some. Then there's long term repeatability. &amp;quot;Long-term
stability&amp;quot; is in the datasheet as &amp;plusmn;0.5% a year, so given identical conditions
today and a year later, there could be a slight difference in RH, no matter
what. There's also something called
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://zone.ni.com/devzone/cda/ph/p/id/227#toc7"&gt;hysteresis&lt;/a&gt;, which is &amp;plusmn;0.3%.
This one's a bit tricky to explain. If the humidity was rising, the reading of
35.7% could have a different meaning than if the humidity was falling. In
either case the value could have been anywhere from 35.4% to 36.0%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may wonder what's the point of having a sensor resolution of 0.1% RH if the
accuracy means it could practically be any old value. Imagine if you had 10 of
these, all measuring. That extra resolution could be used to narrow down what
the humidity was if you looked for a value that fell into the range of all the
accuracy windows of all the sensors. Plus it's not impossible that an increase
in humidity of 0.1% wouldn't be detected, you just need to take it with a grain
of salt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the temperature side of the DHT22 some more, the accuracy,
resolution, and repeatability are all much better at &amp;plusmn;0.2&amp;deg;C, 0.1&amp;deg;C, and &amp;plusmn;0.2&amp;deg;C
according to the datasheet. I'm not quite sure where Adafruit got &amp;plusmn;0.5&amp;deg;C, but
I'm inclined to go with the datasheet. There's no stability or hysteresis
listed, so it looks like the temperature readings should be fairly accurate and
consistent over time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The TGS2600&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the combined Air Quality sensor. It's analogue so it goes through the
AirPi's Analogue-to-Digital Converter (ADC). We need to understand a bit more
about the electronics and AirPi software this time to understand what the value
of &amp;quot;16920.56&amp;quot; means. Looking through the data sheet gives us this formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/tgs2600/formula.png" alt="Rs = (Vc x Rl)/Vout - Rl" width="192" height="58"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;em&gt;Rs&lt;/em&gt; is sensor resistance, Vc is sensor input voltage, &lt;em&gt;Rl&lt;/em&gt; is load
resistance, and &lt;em&gt;Vout&lt;/em&gt; is measured sensor voltage. Looking through the
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/tomhartley/AirPi/blob/non-modular/interfaces/MCP3008/AQSensor.py#L19"&gt;AirPi code&lt;/a&gt;, we see this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-python"&gt;
resistance = (vin/result - 1)*self.pullup
&lt;/pre&gt;You may notice that if you multiply &lt;tt&gt;self.pullup&lt;/tt&gt; inside the brackets you end
up with the formula for the datasheet. You find if you follow the variables in
the code and do comparisons of the AirPi circuit diagram and the &amp;quot;Basic
Measuring Circuit&amp;quot; diagram in the datasheet, that we're looking at the same
things. So that value of 16920.56 is the &lt;em&gt;Rs&lt;/em&gt; value, or the resistance across
the TGS2600 sensor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question then now that we know exactly what 16920 is, is what does it
mean? For that we have to know what the TGS2600 is sensitive to. It says right
at the top of the datasheet &amp;quot;for the detection of Air Contaminants&amp;quot; but we can
be a bit more precise than that. They specifically list sensitivity to methane,
carbon monoxide (CO), iso-butane, ethanol, and hydrogen. Of course how they do
this is a bit round about. They do it by showing this graph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/tgs2600/sensitivity_characteristics.png" alt="TGS2600 Sensitivity Characteristics"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows a link between the concentration of the different chemicals in
parts-per-million (ppm)&amp;mdash;ppm can be thought of like percent, except for one in
one million rather than one in one hundred. It gives us this information in
relation to &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;Rs/Ro&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;, which is the ratio of sensor resistance, which is what
the AirPi actually measures to &amp;quot;sensor resistance in fresh air&amp;quot;. Which is
unfortunate. This tells us the sensor really needs calibration with fresh air
before we have a meaningful reading. How else do we know what the resistance
in fresh air is? And even then, we still don't know what gas has caused the
quality to drop. 50 ppm of CO or 4 ppm of iso-butane?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait! There's more! Next to the graph on sensitivity characteristics
there's this beauty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/tgs2600/temperature_characteristics.png" alt="TGS2600 Temperature/Humidity Dependency"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So not only does the sensor react to air quality, but humidity and temperature
as well. This actually isn't that uncommon, but means a correction factor needs
to be applied to each reading. Happily the DHT22 can be used to work this out.
Say it's 30&amp;deg; out at 50% RH. We read across the x-axis, then interpolate halfway
between the 65% and 35% lines to tell us that in fresh air &lt;em&gt;Rs/Ro&lt;/em&gt; would read
just over 0.9, so call it 0.91. We need to divide the &lt;em&gt;Rs&lt;/em&gt; reading by this
value to correct it to what it would be at the standard 20&amp;deg;C 65% RH they used
for the sensitivity graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need for calibration and taking into account temperature and humidity is
discouraging, but the sensor can still give useful information. Someone using
the data from it simply needs to be aware of these things so that he doesn't
draw incorrect conclusions. For example at the very least the temperature and
humidity corrections should be applied. The fresh air calibration probably
isn't really necessary given that you don't know what gas is affecting it. I
suspect though that it can be worked out approximately by looking at a long
data series that has been corrected for temperature and humidity. The peak &lt;em&gt;Rs&lt;/em&gt;
value measured is probably the &amp;quot;fresh air&amp;quot; quality, or a &amp;quot;close enough&amp;quot; guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may notice that I haven't said anything about accuracy for the TGS2600.
That's because the datasheet doesn't say much about it other than 10 ppm H2
(that's hydrogen). The DHT22 also had an on-board analog to digital conversion
that in this case is being handled by the ADC, which I think has a high enough
resolution that's it's a non-issue. All things considered I suspect that the
ultimate lack of reliable calibration means that accuracy is a non-issue. Just
take the reading with a grain of salt and remember to correct for temperature
and humidity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Light-Dependent Resistor (LDR), GL5528&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one, I have to admit before actually looking into it, I thought was going
to be meaningless. Mostly because I remember playing with an LDR when I was
about 8 to turn lights on and off in the dark of my closet. Because of that I
just could not see how you could use an LDR to get to a Lux reading.
(&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lux"&gt;Lux&lt;/a&gt; is the standard light measure, the
same way that meters are for distance.) However, looking at the
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/PD0001.pdf"&gt;GL5528 datasheet&lt;/a&gt; I was surprised to find that there
actually is a proper relationship between resistance and lux, or illuminance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/ldr/graph.png" alt="GL5528 luminance vs
photo-resistance"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a &lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Log-log_plot"&gt;log-log graph&lt;/a&gt;, there's an
approximately linear relationship between the two which means that if we
calculate the resistance of the LDR, we can estimate the lux fairly reliably.
I use qualitatives like &amp;quot;approximately&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;fairly&amp;quot; because there's that gray
region on the graph&amp;mdash;the relation can be anywhere in there. That's quite the
potential error in there, and the darker it is the greater that uncertainty is
due to the log-log scale. We can still approximate things though and hope for
the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now how to do that approximation. Looking in the
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/tomhartley/AirPi/blob/non-modular/interfaces/MCP3008/LightSensor.py#L14"&gt;AirPi code&lt;/a&gt; I downloaded that matches the directions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-python"&gt;
rs = ((3.3 - vout) / vout) * 5.6
&lt;/pre&gt;To which I say, &amp;quot;what?&amp;quot;, because that's the code that produces the lux number
of &amp;quot;4.91 Lux&amp;quot; I posted above. I believe that's just plain wrong, because
there's two things wrong here. There's nothing taking into account the pull-up
resistor of 2.2K&amp;Omega; for starters. The 5.6 I could imagine to be a calibration
co-efficient, and I suppose that nominally it could take into account that 
resistor, but then what takes care of the log-log relation ship? I'd expect to
see either an &lt;tt&gt;ln()&lt;/tt&gt; or an &lt;tt&gt;exp()&lt;/tt&gt; because of that. It could simplify all of
that in as I haven't worked through the math there yet, but for the same reason
a teacher doesn't like it when you don't show your work, I'm confused. So I set
out to work out what's going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I do is check the code that goes with the updated hardware
revision and
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/tomhartley/AirPi/blob/master/sensors/analogue.py#L41"&gt;see this&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-python"&gt;
resOut = self.pullUp/((vin/vout)-1)
&lt;/pre&gt;Ah ha. This looks better, more like what we say for the TGS2600 above when we
were calculating resistance, except in this case it's a one-over (as in one
divided by) relation. This makes sense because it's a pull-up instead of a
pull-down situation (vin and vout are reversed). On a side note, this sort
of calculation is called a &lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voltage_divider"&gt;voltage divider&lt;/a&gt;. Anyway, when the new software says &amp;quot;7698.96193772 Ohms&amp;quot; for
the light sensor that's exactly what it is. It still needs to be converted to
lux, but at least it's clearer that this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conversion should therefore be pretty straightforward (once the wacky math
on the older software is reversed and the correct resistance value obtained).
It is too, after wrapping one's head around the log-log. Fortunately the fact
that it's log-log works for us, making it easier to deal with. Essentially we
can treat it as a regular linear plot of &lt;em&gt;y = mx + b&lt;/em&gt;, but replacing &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;tt&gt;ln(&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;&lt;tt&gt;)&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;ln(&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;tt&gt;)&lt;/tt&gt; (natural logarithms). At which point it's
only a minor nuisance to fire up Matlab (or Octave) and use &lt;tt&gt;polyfit()&lt;/tt&gt; to work
out a linear regression after reading some values off the graph:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-octave"&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt; polyfit(log([1 2 100]), log([60 40 2.8]), 1)

ans =

   -0.6704    4.1215

&lt;/pre&gt;Plug that into &lt;em&gt;y = mx + b&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/ldr/luxformula1.png" alt="ln(Rs/1000) = -0.6704ln(lux)+4.125" width="418" height="65"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apply some algebra and rearrange to solve for the lux value given resistance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/ldr/luxformula2.png" alt="lux = e^a, a = (ln(Rs/1000)-4.125)/-0.6704" width="391" height="80"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viola! This should give me a value that I'm confident reflects reality
somewhat. (&lt;em&gt;Rs&lt;/em&gt; is divided by 1000 because the y-axis of the graph above has K&amp;Omega;
for the units.) I've undoubtedly introduced some error by reading off values
from the graph, but this could be compensated for by adding more values. I
suspect that won't have much of an impact though. Overall I wouldn't use this
or the LDR for life or death situations, but it's close enough. Keep in mind
that if your LDR isn't a 5528 then the function above probably won't be 
correct anymore and should be recalculated off the appropriate datasheet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;UV sensor UVI-01&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really, I think this is one of the coolest bits of the AirPi and I think it's a
shame it's missing from the newer hardware revision. I suppose I can see why
you might replace it with a microphone, but really, UV. How awesome? A measure
of direct sunlight intensity. Potentially something there in calculating
evapo-transpiration, a key part of catchment models. (So that you know how much
rain water can be sucked into the ground!) Also used for working out how much
to water crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right, the sensor. I have no idea electrically how this thing that looks like
an LED is an LED in reverse, but the rest of it makes some sort of sense. It
had better given that last time I spent a good while working out that I plugged
it in backwards. What that means though is that when I see
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/tomhartley/AirPi/blob/non-modular/interfaces/MCP3008/LightSensor.py#L17"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-python"&gt;
sensorVoltage = vout / 471
millivolts = sensorVoltage * 1000
UVI = millivolts * (5.25/20)
&lt;/pre&gt;It actually makes sense. Why divide by 471? That's because that's the ratio
of the two resistors around the CA314 op-amp. According to 
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://airpi.es/step2.php"&gt;the directions&lt;/a&gt; you're supposed to use a 10K&amp;Omega; and
a 4.7M&amp;Omega; for R1 and R2 respectively, that's a ratio of 470, or the amplification
ratio. It's specifically that ratio that's important so you could essentially
use anything in the 1K&amp;Omega; to 30K&amp;Omega; range for R1 as long as R2 was 470 times
greater. Can't make 470 times? Edit that line of code with the 471 divider. (I
used 1K&amp;Omega; and 470K&amp;Omega;, because the Maplin resistor kit doesn't go over 1M&amp;Omega;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi/op-amp circuit.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then why multiply by 1000? That's to get the reading in mV. Because unlike the
previous sensors, which measure by resistance, the UVI-01 is a direct voltage
reading. Which is why the third line of code there is a multiplication by a
factor. That's a factory standard calibration. You can see it in the following
graph from the &lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/UVI-01-E.pdf"&gt;datasheet&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/sensors/uv/uv.png"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/uv/uv_small.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Click for a graph you can actually read...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four very linear lines, for 0.5M&amp;Omega;, 1M&amp;Omega;, 2M&amp;Omega;, and 3M&amp;Omega;, resistor put in
parallel with the UVI-01. The AirPi directions follow the factory
recommendation and use a 1M&amp;Omega; resistor. It's just a matter of reading off the
purple lines to get the 5.25 and 20 as the slope of the line, it's very
convenient as there's no y-intercept. Just read over and down from the 20.00,
and there we have it. A very nice, easy sensor to read with what appears to be
a fairly reliable direct reading of
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultraviolet_index"&gt;UV Index&lt;/a&gt;, or UVI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's just one caveat&amp;mdash;&amp;quot;Inaccuracy: 15&lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&amp;quot;. So given higher levels of UV, i.e.,
when it's more critical, the accuracy goes down. At least, that's how I read
it. So on normal day with a UVI of 5, it could be somewhere between 4.25 and
5.75. That window gets bigger at higher readings. Although to be fair, if we
actually look at the scale on that nice Wikipedia link, at higher values of
UVI, we'd be roasting to a crisp anyway, no matter the accuracy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply knowing the UVI value is up there is enough. Given we know about the
inaccuracy though we can stick some error bars on there and be informed. It's
still probably more reliable than a TGS2600 or an LDR because it doesn't
require a specific calibration. Full steam ahead for knowing when you need
sunblock!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;BMP085 pressure sensor&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://www.adafruit.com/products/391"&gt;Adafruit favorite&lt;/a&gt;. I
immediately like it for &lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/BMP085_DataSheet_Rev.1.0_01July2008.pdf"&gt;another reason&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;quot;Fully calibrated&amp;quot;. What they do is they run a calibration of
the sensor in the factory and burn the calibration co-efficients into the chip.
When the AirPi software reads the value off the pressure transducer, it then
applies this in-built calibration. We can therefore be reasonably confident in
the value being obtained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided we're aware of the inherent sensor accuracy and resolution. In this
case the datasheet says typically &amp;plusmn;1.0 hPa with a maximum of &amp;plusmn;2.5 hPa for
pressure between 700 and 1100 hPa between 0&amp;deg;C and 60&amp;deg;C. This gets a bit worse
at even lower pressures (300 to 700 hPa a maximum of &amp;plusmn;3.0 hPa) and temperatures
(300 to 1100 hPa at -20&amp;deg;C to 0&amp;deg;C typically &amp;plusmn;1.5 hPa  and a maximum of &amp;plusmn;4.0
hPa). For the temperature readings that the BMP085 takes we're looking at
typically &amp;plusmn;0.5&amp;deg;C with a maximum of &amp;plusmn;1.5&amp;deg;C. (This is a little bit worse than the
DHT22.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BMP085 also has one other interesting setting, which is oversampling.
(&amp;quot;mode&amp;quot; in the AirPi software.) The sensor in this case can be told to take
multiple readings internally and return an average value. Because they're very
close in time the assumption is that they're effectively the same reading (i.e.
the pressure won't have changed much) and so averaging will cancel out any
other effects that would introduce noise into the pressure reading. By default
the AirPi uses the setting that averages 2 readings. The sensor is capable of
doing a maximum of 8 readings internally, but there's a penalty in time and
power consumption for doing this. The latter probably has more impact because
the software isn't running as quickly as 25 ms resolution (the time for 8
readings).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So taking this all into account, the temperature reading won't be so good, but
the pressure reading should be excellent. Remember that
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atmospheric_pressure#Standard_atmospheric_pressure"&gt;standard atmospheric pressure&lt;/a&gt; is 1013.25 hPa, which means that &amp;plusmn;1.0 hPa is
actually &amp;plusmn;0.1%. As pressure gets lower that becomes a slightly higher fraction,
but even under the worst of conditions (cold weather and low pressure) we're
still only talking about &amp;plusmn;0.5% error or so. I feel here Bosch lives up to the
brand name recognition and delivers a good product. It's similar to the feeling
I got using
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://www.ge-mcs.com/en/pressure-and-level/depth-and-level/ptxpdcr-1830.html"&gt;GE Sensing PDCR 1830 Druck Pressure Sensors&lt;/a&gt; in academic research. (Although
there it's &amp;plusmn;0.06% error!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing is to talk bout how the AirPi software uses the data from the
sensor. The data sheet suggests two uses and both are implemented in the AirPi
software. The first is to use the pressure to calculate the altitude. The
higher up you are the lower the pressure will be and this expresses as an
exponential function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/bmp085/pressure_alt.png" alt="altitude = 44330 x (1-(p/p0)^(1/5.255))" width="394" height="76"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;em&gt;p0&lt;/em&gt; is pressure at sea level, so 1013.25 hPa and &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt; is the pressure
reading from the sensor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second use is to calculate the pressure at sea level given a known
altitude:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/sensors/bmp085/pressure_sea.png" alt="p0 = p / ((1 - altitude/44330)^5.255)" width="247" height="63"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's the second of these which is used by default in the AirPi software,
assuming an altitude of 35 m above sea level. Sheffield is a hilly place and as
a result altitude over the area actually varies quite a bit. I think my house
is a bit higher given that when the AirPi says 98.2 hPa, the barometer on my
wall reads 97.1 hPa. Which brings me to my point here: I'd rather have the
pressure reading as is, just like the wall barometer. While the sensor is
accurate enough to give a precise pressure reading, the readings are really
only interesting to me for the trends they show. That is to say, to help me
predict the weather! (Typically low pressure = bad weather, high pressure =
good weather.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The rest of the sensors&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've only gone through the sensors I have on my AirPi breadboard. I leave the
remaining microphone, NO and CO meters, as an exercise for the reader. Or
another later article. What I have here is enough so that in a post or two I
can look at my data and see what there is to see.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two major things of interesting in a monitoring setup like this.
What's happening now, and what's happened previously. Here's what I think
everything is best for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DHT22 Humidity: Trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DHT22 Temperature: Current readings and trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TGS2600: Trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LDR (GL5528): Trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UVI-01: Current readings and trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BMP085 Pressure:  Current readings and trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BMP085 Temperature: Trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that overall what's going to be really exciting is looking at
magnitude of change over time, rather than looking at specific values. Stay
tuned to see what my room has been like since I built the AirPi!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script src="https://google-code-prettify.googlecode.com/svn/loader/run_prettify.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-02-25:posts/2014/02/25/airpisensors/</guid><category>airpi</category><category>hardware</category><category>pi-tronics</category><category>environmental</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category></item><item><title>AirPi Update - A kit!</title><link>/posts/2014/02/14/airpiupdate/</link><description>

&lt;!--%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/02/07/airpi1/"&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt; I introduced everyone to the
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://airpi.es/"&gt;AirPi&lt;/a&gt;, an open environmental sensor platform. They
provide a list of components, schematics, and software for you to build a
rather tiny Pi sized weather station. I went through the process of ordering
the parts and bread-boarding it up before. They also, however, provide
everything in a convenient ready-to-solder kit, which is what I'll be writing
about today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamish went over to Cambridge for
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://www.facebook.com/cambridgeraspberryjam"&gt;CamJam&lt;/a&gt;, the local
RaspberryJam they've got over there. He had the chance to meet with some
interesting folks, including Tom Hartley, one of the AirPi developers. He also
picked up one of those kits so that I had something new to play with while
some data records on my breadboard system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/box.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/box.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Kitbox&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/boxcontents.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/boxcontents.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;And all the stuff in it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to know is that this is AirPi v1.2. This isn't what the
directions on the site are currently for. This is a newer hardware revision,
with a slightly different load-out. The primary difference is that the UV sensor
has been replaced with a microphone. I'm not too sure about this change, but it
means that the CA314 op-amp has been replaced with a MCP6283.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/pcbtop.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/pcbtop.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PCB top&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/pcbbottom.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/pcbbottom.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;PCB bottom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also see there on the PCB spots for two LEDs (LED1 and LED2). These
aren't new hardware per-say, they just may be new to you. The LEDs are included
in the assembly directions, I simply didn't include them as I didn't feel the
need for more blinking lights on the Pi. It's customisable hardware after
all&amp;mdash;gotta take advantage of that! The AirPi does itself. The kit comes with
the separate MICS-2710 (NO2) and MICS-5525 (CO) sensors, which I couldn't get
for my breadboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/mostlydone.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/mostlydone.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Just about everything soldered on&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/mostlydonebottom.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/mostlydonebottom.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You can see where the board has melted some&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This took me about an hour and a half to do. The only thing that's not soldered
yet is the connector for the Pi. I was very involved in actually sorting
everything out though that I forgot to take more pictures of the process. It's
like following a set of LEGO directions so from that point of view it's easy.
The catch is that soldering is sometimes hard. Which, as I've pointed out
above, has led to me melting the board a little in some places, and odd shaped
blobs of solder in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see on the PCB the empty TGS2600 location, which is fine as it's been
replaced with the MICS sensors. You can also see one resistor of a different
color. That's because somehow, probably sometime between the kit being made and
me getting it, a 330&amp;Omega; resistor was lost. Fortunately my trusty Maplin kit of
resistors saves the day, but I must say that working out which resistor was
which was the hardest part of doing this kit. The colors on the printed card
are hard to distinguish, and it's hard to distinguish them on the resistors
themselves. Impossible on the tiny little ones, like the 100&amp;Omega; and 100K&amp;Omega;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/done.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/done.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Done!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/donebottom.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/donebottom.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;And the reverse&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soldering on the Pi connector was interesting. 26 very tightly spaced little
contacts that I soldered from the bottom. That side with a huge chunk of
plastic in the way. Somehow it seemed like a better idea than approaching it
from the top, but I don't know really. I used a GPIO ribbon cable to work out
how much the connector on the bottom needed to stick through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/onapi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/onapi.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sticking it on a pi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/onapiside.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/onapiside.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A pretty compact package&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After putting the AirPi on top of a Pi, I realised that the placing GPIO header
placing turned out to be near perfect. But due to dumb luck. If I hadn't had
the GPIO ribbon idea, I would have would up having to re-solder it. You can see
how darn near it is to there not being enough clearance. Ouch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/onapiside2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/onapiside2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Eeek! That's close!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then to test if it works. It's important to note that the different board
has a different software version to go with it, this time off of the trunk of
the &lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/tomhartley/AirPi"&gt;Git repository&lt;/a&gt;. Configuring is
easier this time around though as the software matches the hardware perfectly.
Only two minor configuration changes are necessary. One in sensors.cfg to set
the correct I2C bus. The other in outputs.cfg to disable Xively as I'm only
testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/takingareading.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/takingareading.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I put it in my half disassembled LEGO case for powering up to test&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It runs perfectly out of the box! You can see the green LED lighting up on a
reading. Output is shown below. I'm not entirely convinced the temperature is
correct, but everything else is reasonable, I think... At this point I struggle
from the same problem as I did last time, which is I still haven't quite worked
out how to interpret the data. I admit though that this version of the software
is more honest. Calling it Ohms for an analogue sensor reading without
calibration is probably the correct way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;Time: 2014-02-11 20:37:56.611572
Temperature: 32.4 C
Pressure: 977.71 hPa
Relative_Humidity: 25.7000007629 %
Light_Level: 7698.96193772 Ohms
Nitrogen_Dioxide: 7607.57314974 Ohms
Carbon_Monoxide: 301176.470588 Ohms
Volume: 90.3225806452 mV
Uploaded successfully&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm not entirely convinced about the utility of the microphone. Maybe an
indirect measure of wind? All told though a pleasant and funkit to build. The
difficulty is about average. Some bits to solder are tricky, but nothing's
impossible, especially if you have some previous experience. This kit has now
been sent off to Lubo, our electronics specialist, for additional compatibility
testing with the MoPi. In the meantime I continue to collect data from my
breadboard prototype to see what I can do with it. Stay tuned for a report!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi1.2/theend.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi1.2/thumbs/theend.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The end&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-02-14:posts/2014/02/14/airpiupdate/</guid><category>airpi</category><category>hardware</category><category>pi-tronics</category><category>environmental</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category></item><item><title>Building an AirPi</title><link>/posts/2014/02/07/airpi1/</link><description>

&lt;!--%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://airpi.es/"&gt;AirPi&lt;/a&gt; is an open hardware environmental sensor
platform. Weather and air quality monitoring using low cost components that
you can order and then assemble yourself. Really it's a pretty neat project.
What they do is give you a component list and a schematic diagram (and PCB
layout too, if you're into that) so that you have quite a deal of flexibility
in what your monitoring station can do. The complete list includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temperature&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humidity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Light level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UV level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General air quality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NO2 level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CO level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi/atairpi.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;An AirPi promo photo...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, what you build yourself almost never looks as nice as what the stock
photo looks like. For starters, I know I haven't got easy access to PCB
fabrication so I'm going to be building a breadboard AirPi. The first step to
that is ordering components. On the AirPi site they give a
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://airpi.es/step1.php"&gt;good list&lt;/a&gt; of the components you need to have.
Most stuff can be ordered easily enough either through places like
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://uk.rs-online.com/"&gt;RS Components&lt;/a&gt; or the rest off of eBay shops.
Those were my sources, and in the end only one part (the UV sensor) had to come
from outside the UK. I got a multi-resistor pack and breadboard from Maplin
rather than eBay as that was a bit easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind though that the component list on that page &lt;b&gt;isn't exhaustive&lt;/b&gt;.
I found out only on reading the assembly directions that a bit more was
necessary, particularly to use the UV sensor you also need 0.1uF capacitor
and a CA314 op-amp. The list also doesn't give all the resistors, hence the
multi-pack from Maplin. There's no specific direction about what LDR (Light
Dependant Resistor) either. Based off of comments in the forums I ordered
a pack of GL5528, which have a light resistance of 10K-20K&amp;Omega; and a darkness
resistance of 1M&amp;Omega;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi/components.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi/components_thumb.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Here are all the components&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to all the bits above and the breadboard, I ordered an
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/111260606543"&gt;Adafruit cobbler clone&lt;/a&gt; and some
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://www.ebay.co.uk/itm/231080275924"&gt;solid core jumper wires&lt;/a&gt; so that I
could at least do a tidy breadboard. I was unable to order the NO2 or CO
sensors as the only folks who sell them are in the states and the shipping
was killer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So. On to building! Unfortunately, not all shipping times are equal and I
wanted to get started playing so my first prototype only has the air quality
sensor and the light level sensor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi/prototype1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi/prototype1_thumb.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;My solid core wires hadn't arrived yet either, so messy!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When almost everything had arrived, I started to build prototype 2. All I was
missing was the UV sensor. By the time I finished building though, the sensor
had arrived and I added it in as well. Working on the breadboard ends up being
something of a logic puzzle. How do I get things where I want them, using a
minimum of wire? Without short-circuiting? Or having things stick up? Despite
already having some practice and familiarity with the circuit from building
prototype 1, prototype 2 definitely took longer to build. Lots of cross
checking &lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/2600pdf.pdf"&gt;several&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/21295d.pdf"&gt;of&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/DHT22.pdf"&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/fn957.pdf"&gt;different&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/airpi-files/UVI-01-E.pdf"&gt;datasheets&lt;/a&gt;. A digital multi-meter was a
good friend as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/airpi/prototype2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi/prototype2_thumb.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Much nicer!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things considered the AirPi directions are really quite good. It took so
long because it's a matter of having confidence that I'd done it right. Combine
that with the logic puzzle of individual sensor placement. As the directions
are given on a sensor-by-sensor basis, there's no sense of when you can connect
things together to make a tidier circuit. The fact that you can jump from the
+5V of the air quality sensor to the +5V of the op-amp is incredibly handy if
you, like I've done, place them close together on the breadboard, &lt;em&gt;and you
notice it&lt;/em&gt;. Things like that that take up the time, and then cross-checking it
to make sure it's right takes up even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately in the end I only had three real electrical mysteries (aside from
plugging things in in the wrong spot). The first was that I misinterpreted what
had to be done with the light level sensor. The directions describe its
connection in text only and it just confused me. They make sense now though...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second issue doesn't really have anything to do with the AirPi. The cobbler
I've got has GPIO pins 9 and 17 swapped on the PCB labeling, and testing with a
multimeter they seem to do neither. This is a ground and +3.3V fortunately, but
connecting the ground on the pressure transducer to what may have been +3.3V
accidentally... not so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi/badpins.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Backwards! Yikes!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My third electrical mystery was much more annoying than either of those two.
The long story short is that I had the UV sensor plugged in backwards. The long
leg goes to pin 3, and the short leg connects to ground. Unfortunately, to 
figure out this was the case I had to go and 'debug' the rest of the UV
circuit. Which is fine in principle, until you realize that before I started
this I had no idea how an op-amp worked or what it really does. (Yes, the name
is kind of an indicator, but that really doesn't explain the electronics.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately Chris Gammell has an
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://chrisgammell.com/how-does-an-op-amp-work-part-1/"&gt;excellent
explanation&lt;/a&gt; that made about 60% sense to me. I'll see if I can summarize my
understanding... An op-amp takes a voltage level (in this case from the UV
sensor) and multiplies it (approximately) by the ratio of the resistors between
it and ground and it and the op-amp output. This is done with a feedback loop
over the input to output. Sort of. Anyway, the directions mentioning &amp;quot;470 times&amp;quot;
is referring to this multiplication factor of the sensor output, and is why I
could use 1K&amp;Omega; and 470K&amp;Omega; resistors instead of the 10K&amp;Omega; and 4.7M&amp;Omega; resistors they
did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/airpi/op-amp circuit.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Roughly what an op-amp does...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other effects that come into play, I don't really understand all of
this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As near as I can tell the multiplication works as the op-amp is really an &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;oscillator. The resistor that links the op-amp output and the pin of the &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;op-amp that's not attached to whatever it is you want to multiply causes, for &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;example, an over-voltage. This triggers a state change to under-voltage. The &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;resistor carries this back across which causes over-voltage again. This all &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;happens very rapidly (oscillates!) and results in an even voltage thats the &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;multiplied output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

 &lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Chris' explanation has the signal being amplified attached to the &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&amp;quot;inverting input&amp;quot; while the AirPi has the UV output connected to the &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&amp;quot;non-inverting input&amp;quot;. I think this has to do with how the UV sensor is a &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;diode and we're connecting one end to ground.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;/ul&gt;

 &lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The capacitor in the circuit (not pictured here) has to do with &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;stabilizing the feedback loop because of the response speed of the UV sensor.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The resistor in parallel with the UV sensor ensures a minimum current &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;level. The higher that resistor is, the greater the voltage because of &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;Ohm's law 1/Rtotal = 1/Ra + 1/Rb. I think this explains that graph on the &lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;datasheet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me on to the thing I wish most from the AirPi project: &lt;b&gt;an
explanation of why and how things work&lt;/b&gt;. Right now it's a really nice
monitoring tool, which you could use to learn about the environment. But it
could be an electronics teaching tool as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that's enough boring electronics. On to software! There's a set of
directions on the AirPi page to get you started. It includes installing all the
dependencies which is pretty good. I did all of that except for the 'eeml'
steps - these are for connecting to &lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://xively.com/"&gt;Xively&lt;/a&gt;. This is the
service AirPi uses for storing and distributing stuff. It looked a bit complex
for getting started though, which is why I've skipped it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the dependencies are installed and the AirPi
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/tomhartley/AirPi.git"&gt;Git Repository&lt;/a&gt; has been cloned, the
first step is configuring AirPi.cfg. There's a bit more to it than the
directions let on though. You may need to edit the I2CBus parameter, I had to
change it to 1 to get it to work with my Model A. The UVI-01 ADCPin is
incorrect with respect to the assembly directions, it should be 3 not 4. I also
had to disable the MICS sensors as I don't have these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's also a small bug in Upload.py with regards to the AirQuality pull-up
resistor. Line 118 should be changed from&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-python"&gt;
airSensor = AQSensor.AQSensor(adc,AQADC,pullup)
&lt;/pre&gt;to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-python"&gt;
airSensor = AQSensor.AQSensor(adc,AQADC,pullup=pullup)
&lt;/pre&gt;Since I didn't do the eeml stuff, I also needed to comment out the eeml imports
at the start of Upload.py. Once that's done though it runs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;Temp-DHT:       26.1 C
Humidity:       35.7 %
Air Quality:    16920.56
Light Level:    4.91 Lux
UV Level:       0.48 UVI
Temp-BMP:       25.6 C
Pressure:       97912.6 Pa
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An AirPi built and running! The question is where we go from here? I'm planning
to now collect data for a bit and see if I can massage it and get something
neat out of it. What does Air Quality 16920 even mean? I'll want to check the
calibration of the sensors in general and make sure it's not all nonsense. For
example, I'll use some thermometers and a barometer to cross check those
readings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm also going to look into altering the software. A capability to log and
display info without going through a third party service would be nice. I know
the logging should be possible at least! I also just did a blog post about
&lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/01/25/raingauge/"&gt;connecting a raingauge&lt;/a&gt; to the Pi. I'm pretty
certain that can be added into the AirPi setup. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script src="https://google-code-prettify.googlecode.com/svn/loader/run_prettify.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-02-07:posts/2014/02/07/airpi1/</guid><category>airpi</category><category>hardware</category><category>pi-tronics</category><category>environmental</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category></item><item><title>Connecting a Rain Gauge</title><link>/posts/2014/01/25/raingauge/</link><description>

&lt;!--%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A what? A rain gauge. It counts the depth of rainfall per unit area. So it
might report that over the last 24 hours there were 2 mm of rainfall per
meter squared. Over an area the size of Sheffield (around 300 km&lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;2), that
translates to 600,000 cubic meters or on the order of 240 Olympic size swimming
pools. That sounds like a lot, but realistically when you consider that the
River Don is 110 km long, that volume of water isn't so much. The floods here
in June 2007 were the result of over &lt;em&gt;200&lt;/em&gt; mm of rainfall in two weeks.
60,000,000 m&lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;3 for just Sheffield, combined with the much greater surrounding
area... Now we can see why having a rain gauge might be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/rain/tippingbucket.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/rain/tippingbucket_small.jpg" alt="Inside a tipping bucket rain gauge"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does a rain gauge work? There are a few different types, but most common
and what I've got is called a
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tipping_bucket_rain_gauge#Tipping_bucket_rain_gauge"&gt;tipping bucket rain gauge&lt;/a&gt;. Basically there's a little see-saw inside. The rain
fills up a bucket on one end and it tips over so that it empties and the bucket
on the other side starts to fill. Each time the bucket tips it passes a magnet
over a &lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reed_switch"&gt;reed switch&lt;/a&gt; making a
momentary electrical connection. The buckets are calibrated to a volume of
water, which means if you can count how many times the switch closes you know
how much rainfall there's been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/rain/reedswitch.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/rain/reedswitch_small.jpg" alt="The rain gauge's reed switch"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rain gauge I've been showing here is one you can have for a fiver from
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://www.maplin.co.uk/p/maplin-replacement-rain-gauge-for-n25frn85fyn96gy-n77nf"&gt;Maplin&lt;/a&gt;. It has an RJ-11 plug on the end you'll probably need to cut off to
connect it to the Pi. Still, This suprisingly low cost means anyone can have a
play at weather monitoring, and personally I've always found rain to be pretty
neat. Onwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically what it boils down to is that each tip of the bucket in the rain
gauge is identical to a button press. We can easily then connect the gauge as
if it were a button. I've connected mine to ground and GPIO 17. After that all
we need to do then is to monitor for button presses which is pretty straight
forward. It can be done two ways. A continuous loop can run checking the value
of the GPIO. This is pretty resource intensive. Or we can use GPIO interrupts,
similar to what I did in the &lt;a class="cow-non-existant-url" href="/posts/2014/01/18/3dasintv/"&gt;3D project&lt;/a&gt;. This
is where closing the circuit (pressing the button, the bucket tipping) triggers
a software event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/rain/connection.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/rain/connection_small.jpg" alt="The electrical connection for the gauge"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://raspi.tv/2013/how-to-use-interrupts-with-python-on-the-raspberry-pi-and-rpi-gpio"&gt;RasPi.TV&lt;/a&gt; has written a quite nice article on how to use interrupts with
Python. The &lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/RPi.GPIO"&gt;RPi.GPIO&lt;/a&gt; function library
has a simple call to register listening for interrupts on a given PIN:
&lt;tt&gt;GPIO.add&lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;event&lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;detect&lt;/tt&gt;. This makes it dirt simple to create a monitoring
program. I've uploaded the code I've written to
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://github.com/hamishcunningham/pi-tronics/blob/master/environment/rain.py"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, but I'll go over the important bits here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-python"&gt;
GPIO.setmode(GPIO.BCM)  
GPIO.setup(PIN, GPIO.IN, pull_up_down=GPIO.PUD_UP)
&lt;/pre&gt;This is pretty standard and if you've done any GPIO work before you should
recognize it as initializing the GPIO. The &lt;tt&gt;setup&lt;/tt&gt; function here tells the
system we'll be using &lt;tt&gt;PIN&lt;/tt&gt; (17) for input, and that we should use it in
pull-up mode. That is to say, we connect the internal resitor attached to the
pin to +3.3 V. This allows it to be clear when the rain gauge closes the
circuit to ground that there's been a change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-python"&gt;
# variable to keep track of how much rain
rain = 0

# the call back function for each bucket tip
def cb(channel):
	global rain
	rain = rain + CALIBRATION

# register the call back for pin interrupts
GPIO.add_event_detect(PIN, GPIO.FALLING, callback=cb, bouncetime=300)
&lt;/pre&gt;We have a variable &lt;tt&gt;rain&lt;/tt&gt; that is a counter for the amount of rainfall. We then
have a function (&lt;tt&gt;cb&lt;/tt&gt;) that adds the bucket amount to it, the &lt;tt&gt;CALIBRATION&lt;/tt&gt;
variable which for this gauge is 0.2794 mm per tip. The &lt;tt&gt;add&lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;event&lt;span class="cow-escape"&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;detect&lt;/tt&gt;
function then sets up the interrupt listening on &lt;tt&gt;PIN&lt;/tt&gt;. Because we've set the
pin in pull-up mode, we're listening for a &lt;em&gt;falling edge&lt;/em&gt;, that is the
transition from +3.3 V to 0 V. When this occurs we'll call the &lt;em&gt;callback&lt;/em&gt;
function &lt;tt&gt;cb&lt;/tt&gt;. The &lt;tt&gt;bouncetime&lt;/tt&gt; specifies that the &lt;tt&gt;cb&lt;/tt&gt; can't be called any
more frequently than once every 300 ms. This prevents counting a rapid
alteration between switch states, called bouncing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program output is a CSV log file which in column A has a unix timestamp,
and in column B has a rainfall amount. I've set it up to log every 5 seconds,
but really that can be a much longer minute or 5 minute interval even. I like
the higher frequency because if it's raining really hard, you can't catch small
temporal variations with a longer monitoring frequency. It's easy in comparison
though to go from 5 second to 5 minute readings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing to bear in mind is that how the program is that while the
bucket in the gauge fills up slowly, you only get an instantaneous result.
There won't have been 0.2794 mm of rain in the last 5 seconds, but instead it
will have occured in the interval since the last reading. This is a
post-processing consideration if you're interested in producing rainfall over
time graphs, but isn't an issue for totals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/environment/rain/outdoors.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/rain/outdoors_small.jpg" alt="The gauge placed outside"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some minor comments about rain gauge placement. Higher is better. They should
be secured, and outside of what's called a building's shadow. Rain can be
carried by the wind and if the wind is coming from the other side of the
building the reading's likely to be off. Bearing all that in mind, I can't
meet any of those conditions properly. My rain gauge is at least outside
though. Let's look at some of the data. (I've plotted it quickly using
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://www.gnu.org/software/octave/"&gt;Octave&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/rain/23rd.png" alt="Rain on the 23rd"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some teething problems. The above graph goes from 0900 on the 23rd
to 0900 on the 24th. I know for a fact there was no rainfall that evening.
Indeed, it was dry as a bone and most small puddles had evaporated. I suspect
maybe that the wind or cold weather was having an effect, but I'm really not
sure. In the meantime I'm keeping an eye out for false readings. Maybe an
interrupt bug?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/environment/rain/24th.png" alt="Rain on the 24th"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignoring them, the data is actually pretty good. According to this figure, last
night (from around 1700 to 2200) we had around 7 mm of rainfall. That's a
fairly average rainfall and I actually remember it happening. The value also
compares favorably to other rain gauges I have access to. They're a few km away
and reported 6 to 6.4 mm of rainfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fun project if you're in Sheffield, you can compare how much rain you're
recording to the &lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://twitter.com/WPWeather"&gt;Weston Park Museum's weather
station&lt;/a&gt;! There are other monitoring stations around the country and world a
little bit of Googling should help out there.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;script src="https://google-code-prettify.googlecode.com/svn/loader/run_prettify.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-01-25:posts/2014/01/25/raingauge/</guid><category>hardware</category><category>pi-tronics</category><category>environmental</category><category>rain</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category></item><item><title>3D? As in TV?</title><link>/posts/2014/01/18/3dasintv/</link><description>

&lt;!--%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A year or two ago I connected a small 132x32 pixel LCD display to one of my
Raspberry Pis. The idea behind it was that I could use it to display small
status updates or anything else I wanted. Mostly from that aspect it ended up
being a clock.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/3d/tv/clock_big.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/3d/tv/clock_small.jpg" alt="A rather fancy clock"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I got some code written for text, my next thought was &amp;quot;could I do video?&amp;quot;
There were a few hurdles there to overcome as well. Codec? Framerate? I ended
making up a solution where I read in 2-bit (black and white) bitmap image and
displayed it. Repeat 24 times a second and you have video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/3d/tv/frames.gif" alt="Raw frames"&gt;
&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/3d/tv/video.gif" alt="Video in action"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed something interesting though, in that I could push out images a lot
faster than 24 FPS. I could reach just over the 120 FPS. This is the magic
number for what's known as
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Active_shutter_3D_system"&gt;active 3D TV&lt;/a&gt;. In
Active 3D, the special glasses effectively blank out one eye than the other
rapidly. At the same time the TV is showing the left eye, right, left, right,
etc., at the same speed. (3D in movie theatres, for example
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RealD_Cinema"&gt;RealD 3D&lt;/a&gt;, typically uses
polarized light.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/3d/tv/animation.gif" alt="Active 3D"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways that active glasses are controlled by TVs. The first,
impractical way is radio. Typically Bluetooth. The other way, which fits right
in the realm of hacker electronics, is Infrared. (Just like a remote control!)
Knowing this then I needed a was an infrared transmission from the Pi to the
glasses, and then to match this up with the software I'd already written to
display video. The latter, is easy. The former, not so much so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first stumbling block is the infrared transmission signal. Like a remote
control, it's also a specially coded signal. And like for TVs, many makers
have different signals for their glasses. Fortunately, someone has already
made an
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://cmst.curtin.edu.au/local/docs/pubs/2011-17-woods-helliwell-3D-Sync-IR.pdf"&gt;analysis&lt;/a&gt; of the different signals using an oscilloscope. I managed to find a
reasonably priced pair of nVidia 3D glases. The protocol for them looks like
this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/3d/tv/nvidia protocol.png" alt="nVidia 3D glasses Infrared Protocol"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the timing of those infrared pulses is in &lt;em&gt;micro&lt;/em&gt;seconds. This is
a small problem. The Pi can't consistently execute code at microsecond timing.
Millisecond's about the best it can do because Raspbian isn't what's called a
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real-time_operating_system"&gt;Real-time operating
system&lt;/a&gt;. It spends a lot of time instead cycling between different tasks, any
of which can call for CPU time at any moment and interrupting whatever else is
happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a real-time situation like sending a infrared signal, we can't have the
kernel deciding to take a pause in the middle to do something else.
Fortunately, most microcontrollers are real-time, and so will do exactly
what you tell them to in the order you tell them to.
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://morethanuser.blogspot.co.uk/2013/05/ir-remote-emulator-with-attiny45.html"&gt;More Than User&lt;/a&gt; used an attiny45 to create an infrared remote. I haven't got
one of those, but I do have a
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://estore.ti.com/EZ430-F2013-MSP430-USB-Stick-Development-Tool-P800.aspx"&gt;EZ430-F2013&lt;/a&gt; which is this crazy TI micro-controller in a USB stick format
thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/3d/tv/ez430_big.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/3d/tv/ez430_small.jpg" alt="The EZ430"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EZ430 is very nice in that it comes with a proper development environment
and a &amp;quot;let's blink the LED&amp;quot; code example&amp;mdash;blinking an Infrared LED is what I
wanted to do after all! What I really needed to do then was to learn how to
control blink timing precisely. Things now get a little technical.
Microcontroller programming isn't exactly easy and this was new ground for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I learned that the EZ430 has an onboard 8 MHz clock crystal. What's
neat about this is that you can do something called a &lt;em&gt;timer interrupt&lt;/em&gt;. There
are different ways to go about it, but in general in this case I tell the
EZ430 to count down from X to 0, which X is the number of clock ticks. If I
could put in the number 8,000,000 for X, I'd have an exact timing of 1 second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's not quite that easy though. The counter is only a 16-bit integer which
means I can only count down from 32,767. Fortunately there are clock dividers
available which let you tweak it around. The catch here is that the protocol
has &lt;em&gt;half&lt;/em&gt;microsecond timing. That means I can't divide down directly to 1
MHz timing, and instead can only divide down to 2 MHz timing. My counter then
has to be twice the numbers shown in the protocol diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-c"&gt;
// set up the timer
DCOCTL = CALDCO_8MHZ;
BCSCTL1 = CALBC1_8MHZ;
BCSCTL2 |= DIVS_2; // divide by 4
TACTL = TASSEL_2 + MC_1 + ID_0;
&lt;/pre&gt;At this point I could control the glasses! I was thrilled! The next challenge
then arrises: connecting this to the Pi. Enter &lt;em&gt;input pin interrupts&lt;/em&gt;. The
EZ430 has 8 digital input/output pins. One of them is used as an output for
the infrared LED to talk to the glasses. Another pin I changed to an input,
and then enabled a &lt;em&gt;rising edge&lt;/em&gt; interrupt on it. This means as soon as voltage
at the pin is detected it triggers a code call. From this I can then start the
timer and open one eye and close the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;pre class="prettyprint lang-c"&gt;
// setup interrupt on pin 3
P1IE = BIT3;
P1IES &amp;amp;= ~BIT3; // rising edge
_EINT();
&lt;/pre&gt;Hurrah! I connect the input pin on the EZ430 to a GPIO output from the Pi and
I have glasses control. Now in my video program after a frame is drawn I simply
turn the connected GPIO pin on and off again, triggering an interrupt on the
EZ430, which ends up sending an infred signal to the glasses. Gives a very good
feeling. It may have taken 10 minutes to read this far but it took hours to
learn what I needed on the EZ430 on work it all out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/3d/tv/schematic.png" alt="Devices Schematic"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, my 3D TV doesn't work. As near as I can tell all the electronics
are fine. I just missed one thing. Despite the fact that I can push out 120 FPS
to the LCD there's still a lag for the crystals to change (this is the &amp;quot;response
time&amp;quot; you might have seen advertised on your monitor). The timing on the little
LCD I installed is far greater than the 8 milliseconds needed. Maybe there's a
way around needing 120 FPS for the glasses, but I haven't exactly worked it out
yet. So far now the bits and pieces sit on my desk. A good idea and fun to do.
Close yes, but no cigar. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;script src="https://google-code-prettify.googlecode.com/svn/loader/run_prettify.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-01-18:posts/2014/01/18/3dasintv/</guid><category>hardware</category><category>3d-display</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category></item><item><title>The Cubieboard2</title><link>/posts/2013/12/01/cubieboard2/</link><description>

&lt;!--%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while back we presented a &lt;a class="cow-url" href="/pages/hardware.html"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of different
&amp;quot;Pi-Alikes&amp;quot;. Computers similar to the RaspberryPi - low cost and low power.
The question we set out to answer was &amp;quot;what exactly does 'low power' mean?&amp;quot;
Turns out that for the most part low power was exactly that&amp;mdash;low energy
consumption and low computational power too. The RaspberryPi and its
contemporaries won't break any records but they won't break the bank either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the Cubieboard2. We mentioned that this had been announced and we
finally got our hands on one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="cow-url" href="/images/articles/cubieboard2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/hardware/thumbs/cubieboard2.jpg" alt="Cubieboard2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardware wise, the Cubieboard2 is pretty much identical to the original except
for its &lt;b&gt;A20&lt;/b&gt; dual-core chip and &lt;em&gt;double the RAM&lt;/em&gt; (1 GB). There's the same
ethernet, HDMI, SATA, etc. Instead of Android 4.0.4 it ships with 4.2.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the similarities, the first rule of Cubieboard2 is that it is not
Cubieboard1. Which means that as much as one might want to use the Cubieboard
image, a new SD card image needs to be written. They exist, but were somewhat
harder to find than they were for the original Cubieboard. The
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://linux-sunxi.org/Main_Page"&gt;Sunxi Wiki&lt;/a&gt; isn't well updated for the
Cubieboard2, so I resorted to Google and found
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="http://cubieboard.org/2013/09/07/lubuntu-desktopserver-firmwares-release-for-a20-cubieboard-20130907/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.
In retrospect I should have just started on the Cubieboard pages and followed
the nice big download link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Booting up you see the nice two penguins in the framebuffer that indicate two
CPUs. And then nothing, for quite a long time while the system boots. That was
very disconcerting and I was almost sure something was wrong. With the dual
core CPU you'd expect things to feel faster, but it's hard to tell. Starting
was disconcerting without any output. Starting Chromium was slow, but of course
it would be compared to my desktop with an SSD. Part of the slowness is almost
certainly the SD card. X11 does feel pretty responsive though, and there's not
that much of a slow down when multitasking. That's probably the real benefit of
the second core. That and a tasty 1 GB of RAM make this surprisingly powerful
for the price and size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The two Tux penguins show the kernel recognizing two CPUs...&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/hardware/dualtux.jpg" alt="Look Ma! Dual core!"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best concrete way to compare performance is, of course, a benchmark.
First though, some stupid bug in something-Google made apt-get nearly
impossible to use.
&lt;a class="cow-url" href="https://muffinresearch.co.uk/linux-fix-for-apt-get-update-waiting-for-headers/"&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;
for a fix. That was annoying and necessary to sort out because otherwise there
wouldn't be the necessary software installed to run the benchmarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say that I thought the Cubieboard2 performed better, but I was
absolutely blown away by some of the benchmark results. Network and disk
performance were effectively the same, so we can ignore those. What's really
interesting are the CPU benchmarks. First, integer performance. On a
core-for-core basis it was about the same as a Cubieboard. This means that
overall there's twice the performance when factoring both cores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/hardware/results2/dhry_mips.svg.jpg" alt="Integer Math"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the Cubieboard2 really shines though is in the floating point arena.
Whatever changes they made between the A10 and A20 CPU, Cubieboard and
Cubieboard 2, the two SD card images, it made a huge difference. Results
indicate nearly &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; times the performance. Across both cores that would be
&lt;b&gt;six times&lt;/b&gt; faster over all. (That's 4x faster than the Pi too!) It's
absolutely staggering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/hardware/results2/whet_mflops.svg.jpg" alt="Floating Point Math"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These performance improvements aren't just smoke dust either. There's real
world benefit. bzip2 compression ended up performing about the same. Still,
that's two times the performance considering both cores. There may be a
limiting factor with the SD card here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/hardware/results2/bzip2_min.svg.jpg" alt="bzip2 Compression"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MP3 encoding performance was just fantastic however. Half the time of the
Cubieboard and still significantly faster than the Model B. That's effectively
four times faster when considering both cores. I do believe that what I thought
was faster performance when using the Cubieboard2 is indeed the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="cow-img" src="/images/hardware/results2/lame_min.svg.jpg" alt="MP3 Encoding"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My conclusion? Why would anyone want a Cubieboard anymore? Cubieboard2 all the
way. I sincerely look forward to the next hardware revision of the RaspberryPi
if they can get the same sort of performance improvements.&lt;/p&gt;


</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Fred Sonnenwald</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-12-01:posts/2013/12/01/cubieboard2/</guid><category>hardware</category><category>pi-alikes</category><category>pi</category><category>raspberrypi</category><category>gate</category></item></channel></rss>